Finding Aid for School of Social Work (University of Michigan) Publications 1935-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Social Work (University of Michigan) publications 1935-[ongoing]
University of Michigan. School of Social Work.
Includes brochures, bulletins, college catalogs, lectures from the Fedele F. Fauri Memorial Lecture and the Leon and Josephine Winkelman Lecture series, manuals, newsletters, reports, and student publications. Also contains bulletins from the School of Social Work predecessors such as the Institute of the Health and Social Sciences, Institute of Public and Social Administration, and Institute of Social Work. The Center for the Study of Youth Policy bulletins and newsletters are also included.
0279 Bimu C204 2
4 linear feet
2.34 GB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications are received on a regular basis (Donor 5182 ).
The publications group is open without restriction.
The first curriculum in social work at the University of Michigan was established in 1921. Staff members in sociology developed a curriculum which included background courses in the social sciences and field work. The social work program was legitimized by admission into the Association of Schools of Professional Social Work in 1925. In 1927 the regents of the university authorized a certificate in social work to be awarded to students who completed a year of work experience in addition to the undergraduate degree requirements.
In response to the demands of the Great Depression and the recommendations of a committee of prominent Detroit citizens and social work educators, the university moved to reorganize its social work curriculum. In 1935, with financial support from the Horace H. and Mary A. Rackham Fund and the McGregor Fund, the University of Michigan Institute of Health and Social Sciences was established, and was later renamed the Institute of Public and Social Administration. The institute was located in Detroit, and Robert W. Kelso, who had worked briefly at the Federal Emergency Relief Administration, was appointed as its director.
By 1945, faculty members were urging the restructuring of the Institute of Public and Social Administration and the formation of an Institute of Social Work. In order to explore the possibilities, a committee composed of faculty members from Ann Arbor was created to work with Kelso. As a result of their work, the institute remained in Detroit and designed a curriculum to enlarge the technical side of training for work in the general field of social and public welfare. It became the Institute of Social Work and included courses in social case work, group work, community organization, public welfare, research and statistics, administration, and field work.
In 1950, upon Kelso's retirement, Arthur Dunham served as the institute's acting director. That same year, the University of Michigan and Wayne State University considered merging their social work programs, or expanding one of the programs to handle all graduate education in social work in the Detroit area. After months of negotiation, Wayne State announced plans to strengthen its programs in Detroit, and the University of Michigan to reorganize its social work curriculum. The Institute of Social Work was reconstituted as the School of Social Work under the administrative direction of a dean, and the supervision of a governing faculty of the school. On March 1, 1951, the School of Social Work became the 15th school of the University of Michigan, and operations were transferred from Detroit to Ann Arbor. Fedele F. Fauri was named dean and professor of public welfare administration. He had served as director of the Michigan Department of Social Welfare, and as senior specialist in social welfare and social security of the Legislative Reference Service in Washington, D.C.
During the 1950s, the school expanded its curriculum, hired new faculty members, and strengthened its intra-university ties to the social sciences. The curriculum was enlarged to include courses in psychiatric social work, medical social work, and child welfare. Extension programs were also established in Detroit and throughout the state. Several important faculty members joined the school. Plans for the development of a specialization in group work were enhanced by the appointment of Robert Vinter in 1954. His teaching, research, and writing brought national attention to the school for leadership in education in the practice of social group work. Wilbur J. Cohen joined the faculty in 1956. Cohen had been director of Research and Statistics, Social Security Administration, U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. He came to the school after twenty-one years of federal service. Intra-university connections were improved in 1953 when an interdisciplinary faculty seminar on the research basis of welfare practice was begun. It was funded by the Russell Sage Foundation and headed by David G. French. The seminar resulted in the creation of a Coordinating Committee on Social Welfare Research chaired by sociology Professor Amos Hawley. This committee developed plans for a program of advanced training and research in social work and the social sciences leading to the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in social work.
In the 1960s, social work faculty members served in numerous positions of leadership in shaping national and state social welfare policies. Professor Wilbur Cohen was appointed by President John F. Kennedy as chairman of the Task Force on Health and Social Security, and as assistant secretary for legislation of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. Under President Lyndon B. Johnson, Cohen was appointed secretary of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. Dean Fedele Fauri served as a member of the Ad Hoc Committee on Public Welfare of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, and was elected president of the American Public Welfare Association in 1966. Robert Vinter worked on the State of Michigan Governor's Task Force on Juvenile Delinquency, and as consultant to President Johnson's Committee on Juvenile Delinquency and Youth Crime.
Curriculum changes, re-accreditation, and expanded enrollment occupied the school in the 1960s. The curriculum was broadened to meet the new demands of the decade and included more emphasis on course work rather than field work. The accreditation review spurred greater faculty-student interaction, as student representatives met with various task forces and served as members of the Curriculum Committee. In 1965 students formed the Student Union, which formalized student participation in school decision-making processes, and granted students seats on several school committees. An emphasis on recruitment of minorities resulted in a higher number of minority students and led to the formation of the Association of Black Social Work Students and of the Hispanic student organization, Trabajadores de la Raza. Due to an increase in financial aid opportunities through grants and scholarships, the school experienced a subsequent increase in enrollment. By 1968, the school ranked first among the seventy-five accredited schools of social work in the United States in enrollment, number of full-time students, and the number of M.S.W. degrees granted each year.
In July 1971, Dean Fauri was appointed Vice President for State Relations and Planning at the university, and Associate Dean Vinter served as acting dean. In September 1971, the Regents appointed Phillip Fellin as dean and Richard English and Shiela Feld as assistant deans. The school's governing faculty continued to provide for a Faculty Council, which served in an advisory capacity to the dean on school affairs.
In 1973, the school's ten year re-accreditation review prompted a renewed emphasis on minority recruitment and an assessment of the minority-relevant content of course offerings at the school. The School of Social Work led the university in minority enrollment, as it had done for some time, and reached 21 percent minority enrollment in 1976. Over 68 percent of the student body was comprised of women. In 1976 it was one of only seven schools to receive over 1,000 applications for its master's program, ranking second only to Columbia University. Another outcome of the re-accreditation review was the development of closer ties to other university departments, and to state and local social agencies.
On July 1, 1981, Harold R. Johnson was appointed dean following the retirement of Phillip Fellin. Prior to becoming dean, Johnson had served as director of the Institute of Gerontology from 1974 to 1981. Johnson's appointment marked a change in leadership and direction of the school. Greater prominence and support were given to teaching and research, and service activities were de-emphasized. At a time when schools of social work around the country faced diminishing resources and were being pressed to provide professional social workers with greater skills, the school embarked on a curriculum overhaul. The curriculum was completely revised to provide students with multiple practice skills, expertise in a field of service, and the capacity to assess and evaluate professional practice. The extent of the curriculum revision was expressed in the words of the Council of Social Work Education in its 1983 re-accreditation report. The report called the reforms a "courageous major revision of a well-established curriculum to conform to the reality of social practice knowledge and skills which graduates will be called upon to possess if they are to meet the needs of the profession in the changing world around us."
During Johnson's tenure as dean, from 1981 to 1993, the school continued to promote cultural and ethnic diversity. Those goals continued under Johnson's successor, Paula Allen-Meares who became dean in 1993. Major fundraising initiatives helped to focus research on poverty, racial inequalities, children and families, and also allowed the school to move forward on plans for a new building. In 1995 ground was broken for the new School of Social Work Building, designed by Sims-Varner Associates of Detroit. It was intended to foster a sense of community, with pods of faculty offices arranged around open stairways and the glass walls of its state-of-the-art library open to the lobby, lounge and corridors above. The building was officially dedicated on September 25, 1998.
Further information on the school and its programs can be found at the following URL: http://www.ssw.umich.edu/
Directors and Deans of the School of Social Work
1935-1950 Robert W. Kelso (Director)
1950-1951 Arthur Dunham (Acting Director)
1951-1970 Fedele A. Fauri
1970-1971 Robert Vinter (Acting Dean)
1971-1981 Phillip Fellin
1981-1993 Harold R. Johnson
1993- Paula Allen-Meares
The School of Social Work Publications (4 linear feet) are divided in four series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, Student Organization Publications and Archived Websites. Some publications (or their successors) may no longer be available in print but are available on the school s website.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan. School of Social Work.; University of Michigan. Institute of the Health and Social Sciences.; University of Michigan. Institute of Public and Social Administration.; University of Michigan. Institute of Social Work.; University of Michigan. Center for the Study of Youth Policy.; University of Michigan. Center for the Study of Youth Policy.; Fedele F. Fauri memorial lecture series in child welfare; Leon and Josephine Winkelman lecture.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Institute of the Health and Social Sciences.; University of Michigan. Institute of Public and Social Administration.; University of Michigan. Institute of Social Work.
Catalogs, College.; Lectures.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Reports.; Student publications.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series includes publications published by the School of Social Work such as the bulletins or college catalogs, arranged chronologically; histories; texts of individual lectures sponsored by the school, such as the Fedele F. Fauri Memorial Lecture Series in Child Welfare and the Leon and Josephine Winkelman Lecture series; manuals such as the Blue Book for Social Work Students, Manual for the Professional Practicum and the Student Guide to the Master's in Social Work Degree Program; newsletters such as Newsline and Ongoing; and reports including A Profile of Social Work Graduates and Research in Social Welfare: A Proposed Program for the University of Michigan. Also included in this series under reports are Selected Sections of the Affirmative Action Report for the School of Social Work.
  - Annual Reports
    - 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies
    - A Report on Faculty Research at the University of Michigan School of Social Work
      - 1988-1990, circa 1991 (Box 1)
      - 1990-1992, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - 1952-1993 undated (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - Alternative Curriculum Schedules, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Descriptions of Courses, 1983-1989 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins (College Catalogs)
    - Institute of the Health and Social Services
      - Announcement, 1935-1936 (Box 1)
    - Institute of Public and Social Administration
      - Curriculum in Social Work Announcement, 1939-1946, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Institute of Social Work
      - Announcement, 1946-1951, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - School of Social Work
      - Announcement, 1951-1983, 11 folders (Box 1)
      - Bulletin
        - 1983-1999, 6 folders (Box 1)
        - 2000/01-2001/02 (Box 1)
        - 2002/03-2003/004
        - 2004/05-2005/06 (Box 1)
    - School of Social Work
      - Announcement, 1951-1983, 11 folders (Box 1)
      - Bulletin, 1983-1999, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Directories
    - Building Leadership for a Changing Society, undated (Box 1)
    - Directory and Photographic Roster, 1989-1995, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Histories
    - The First Ten Years, 1935-1945, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Lectures
    - Dorothy Robinson Memorial Lecture
      - Field Teaching: Acculturation and Education for Clinical Social Work Practice by Shirley Cooper, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Fedele F. Fauri Memorial Lecture Series in Child Welfare
      - The Struggle for a Coherent Child Welfare Policy by Winifred Bell, 1985 (Box 1)
      - The Future of Child Welfare: How Will Current Issues and Trends Affect the Decade Ahead by Peter W. Forsythe, 1986 (Box 1)
      - Black Children: Coping in a Racist Society by Alvin F. Poussaint, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Children and the Courts: Salvation or Damnation by Rosemary Barkett, 1988 (Box 1)
      - America's Children: The Homeless, Hungry and Poor by Jonathan Kozol, 1990 (Box 1)
      - Beyond the Rhetoric to Enhanced Child Well Being by Ruth W. Massinga, 1990 (Box 1)
      - Children in Poverty and the Welfare Crises: What Can Be Done with Sander M. Levin, 1992 (no transcript of lecture) (Box 1)
      - Reframing the Practice Task in Child Welfare: Challenges and Opportunities by James K. Whittaker, 1994 (Box 1)
      - The Triumph of History and Politics Over Demography and Social Opportunities Change by Sheila B. Kamerman, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Fedele F. Fauri and Iris M. Fauri Memorial Lecture Series in Child Welfare
      - What is the Goal of Child Welfare Services: Permanency or Self-Sufficiency? by Richard P. Barth, 1995 (no transcript of lecture) (Box 1)
      - Challenges to Children's Well-Being in a Globalizing World: A UNICEF Perspective by Joanne M. Csete, 1998 (Box 1)
    - The Leon and Josephine Winkelman Lecture
      - Aging, Social Class, and Ethnicity by Zena Smith Blau, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Principles and Practice of Hospice Care by Daniel C. Hadlock, 1979 (Box 1)
      - The Ethnic Factor in Delivery of Services to the Aged by Barbara Bryant Solomon, 1980 (Box 1)
      - New Perspectives on Aging and Social Policy by Bernice L. Neugarten, 1982 (Box 1)
      - Creating Coherent Public Policy for the Elderly in a Welfare State by Bent Rold Andersen, 1982 (Box 2)
      - Aging and Society: Notes on the Development of New Understandings by Matilda White Riley, 1983 (Box 2)
      - Diagnosis and Management of Dementias in the Geriatric Patient by Gabe J. Maletta, 1984 (Box 2)
      - A New View of Older Women in America by Mildred M. Seltzer, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Health Care of the Elderly: The Canadian Experience by Theodore Goldberg, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Contradictions and Innovations in Health Care of the Elderly: A Doctor's Dilemma by Gary R. Andrews, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Death and the Law: What is the right to Die? by John H. Pickering, 1989 (Box 2)
      - Gerontic Imperatives: Danger and Opportunity by Olivia P. Maynard, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Understanding Creative Potential in Later Life: Impact on Research, Practice, and Policy by Gene D. Cohen, 1992 (Box 2)
        (video tape, no transcript of lecture)
      - The Acute and Long-Term Care of Minority Elderly: Implications of Health Care Financing Reform by Ronald J. Angel, 1994 (Box 2)
      - Geriatric Prisoners by Herbert A. Rosefield, Jr., 1995 (Box 2)
      - Social Security: Yesterday, Today and Tomorrow by W. Andrew Achenbaum, 1996 (Box 2)
      - The Economic Well-Being of the Elderly in a Changing Society by Martha N. Ozawa, 1996 (Box 2)
      - National Nursing Home Resident Assessment Instrument or What Do You Do with 6 Million Assessments? by Brant E. Fries, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Visiting Scholars Program Welfare and Social Justice
      - Welfare Reform and Social Services: Myth and Reality by Yeheskel 'Zeke' Hasenfeld, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Manuals
    - The Blue Book for Social Work Students, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Guide to the School of Social Work, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Guidelines for Course Planning, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Manual for the Professional Practicum
      - 1986 (Box 2)
      - 1988 revised (Box 2)
      - 1991 (Box 2)
    - Practice Skill Assessment Instrument, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Practice Skill Instruction Manual for Field Instructors and Faculty, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Student Guide to the Master's in Social Work Degree Program, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - Newsline, 1971-1977 (Box 2)
    - Ongoing, 1981-2002, 14 folders (Box 2)
  - Proceedings
    - Strategies in Planning and Implementing Community Corrections Programs, 1971 (Box 2)
    - The University of Michigan School of Social Work and the United Way of America Proposal to the Kellogg Foundation, undated (Box 2)
  - Reports
    - A Comparative Analysis of Welfare Councils, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Guidelines for Social Change: Utilization of Social Science Research in Social Planning and Community Action, Interim Draft, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Detailed Architectural Program for the School of Social Work, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Individual and Group Supervision in Field Instruction, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Information and Decision Processes in Human Service Organizations, Final Report, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Michigan's General Assistance Population: An Interim Report of the General Assistance Termination Project, 1993 (Box 3)
    - A Profile of Social Work Graduates, circa 1974 (Box 3)
    - Report to Commission on Accreditation Council on Social Work Education, 1983 includes Appendix to the Report, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Research in Social Welfare: A Proposed Program for the University of Michigan, 1954 (Box 3)
    - Selected Sections of the Affirmative Action Report for School of Social Work, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Site Visit Report: Reaccreditation Master of Social Work Program, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Strategic Plan, 1990 (Box 3)
    - The University of Michigan School of Social Work Report to the Council on Social Work Education, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Reprints
    - Reprint Series
      - Social Work and Social Welfare, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Symposiums
    - Wilbur J. Cohen Symposium
      - Program 1988 (Box 3)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series includes publications created by sub-units within the School of Social Work. This series includes an alumni publication entitled The Link. This series also contains bulletins and newsletters from the Center for the Study of Youth Policy, which discuss various governmental policies and how they affect children in society. The heading "Development" includes the Prospectus for a New Building for the School of Social Work, which describes the building needs of the School of Social Work but does not include any preliminary drawings.
  - Alumni Organization
    - Newsletters
      - The Link, 1950-1952 (Box 3)
  - Center for the Study of Youth Policy
    - Articles
      - Keeping Kids Out of Secure Detention: The Misuse of Juvenile Detention Has a Profound Impact on Child Welfare, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Bulletins
      - 1987-1992, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Flyers
      - 1992 (Box 3)
    - Newsletters
      - Children's Services Review, vol. 1-5, 1989-1995, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - Infant Mortality in Michigan's Child Welfare System by Kristine Siefert, Ira M. Schwartz and Robert M. Ortega, 1992 (Box 3)
      - Juvenile Arrest, Detention, and Incarceration Trends, 1979-1989, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Michigan Infants in the Child Welfare System: Preliminary Tables by Ira M. Schwartz, Robert M. Ortega and Gideon Fishman, 1992 (Box 3)
      - Michigan's Children Went Missing by Joan M. Abbey, Ira M. Schwartz and Analisa Vestevich, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Reducing Psychiatric Hospitalization for Children and Adolescents in Toledo, Ohio by Ira M. Schwartz and Thomas Wernert, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Center on Poverty, Risk and Mental Health
    - Annual Reports
      - Social Work Research Development Center on Poverty, Risk, and Mental Health at the University of Michigan, 1995-1996, circa 1997 (Box 3)
  - Continuing Education Program
    - Conference Dialogue
      - Separation of Income Maintenance and Social Services in Public Welfare, Undated (Box 3)
    - Conference Schedules 1980 (Box 3)
  - Coordinating Committee on Social Welfare Research
    - Reports
      - Significant Findings on the Impact of the 1957- 58 Recession in Relation to Unemployment Insurance by William Haber, et al., 1959 (Box 3)
  - Degree Programs
    - Doctoral Program
      - Brochures
        - Doctoral Study in Social Work and Social Science, undated (Box 3)
        - General 1982-1986, undated (Box 3)
      - Directories
        - Guide to the Research and Scholarly Interests of the Social Work Faculty
          - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
          - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
      - Flyers
        - Fellowships for Doctoral Study in Social Work and Social Science, undated (Box 3)
      - Newsletters
        - Newsletter, 1977 (Box 3)
      - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Conference
        - Proceedings 1986 (Box 3)
        - Programs
          - Social Science and Social Interaction: Next Steps, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Masters Program
      - Brochures undated (Box 3)
        (includes information regarding dual degrees)
      - Manuals
        - Student Guide to the Master's in Social Work Degree Program
          - 1986-1989 (Box 3)
          - 1994-1995 (Box 3)
          - 1995-1996 (Box 3)
          - 2009-2010
  - Detroit Initiative
    - Directories
      - Guide to Human Services for Immigrants and Refugees in Metropolitan Detroit, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Urban League/University of Michigan (DULUM)
    - Urban Research Series
      - No Sales to Minors, no. 1, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Development
    - Invitations
      - Looking Forward: Building Dedication Ceremony, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Prospectus
      - An Important Naming Opportunity, undated (Box 3)
      - Prospectus for a New Building for the School of Social Work, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Library
    - Handbooks
      - School of Social Work Library, Undated (Box 3)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Day
    - Brochures 1985 (Box 3)
  - Mental Health Community Intervention Program